Brad Melin: Systems Engineer

proto.club / brad@proto.club / +49 151580 12364

I'm a self-taught generalist with over a decade of experience who cares deeply about finding the right problem and solving it in the simplest way possible.

Because I'm relatively outgoing, have a wide range of interests, communicate well, and don't take myself too seriously, I tend to connect easily with many people in an organisation, which enables me to be an effective teammate and leader. I enjoy and have experience with mentoring other engineers, sharing knowledge with technical and non-technical people alike, learning new things, and talking to customers.

Experience

System lead at <u>Fraugster</u>, a fraud-detection startup

October 2020 - March 2023

- Lead development, product, and adoption of graph processing across the company.
- Built tools for machine learning and analytics teams to help them simulate and model fraud.

Tech stack: Go, Parquet, Presto / Athena, Kubernetes, Helm, Kafka.

Staff software engineer at Bain & Company, a management consultancy

September 2019 - September 2020

Technical lead on projects that solved business problems for large corporates. Coached data scientists in my team to be more effective programmers.

Key project:

 Worked on a machine learning + web application to help minimise arbitrage of a client's products across the European market.

Tech stack: Python, Go, React.

Full-stack engineer and technical team lead at <u>Luno</u>, a cryptocurrency exchange and wallet

February 2018 - August 2019

Learned a lot just by being part of a scaling startup, including how to lead a cross-functional team, and maintaining company culture during rapid growth. I fell completely in love with Go, and learned how to be a good technical interviewer. Created and delivered a series of talks to help train our non-technical staff on the tech that we used.

Key projects:

- Decreased customer support requests by designing and implementing a far better search for our help centre, using latent semantic analysis.
- Led a successful overhaul of our website and web app, which required staged rollout and rollback, and touched every part of our stack.
- Designed our first ETL pipeline for ML training, with reproducible runs and easy parameter updates. Used Go for orchestration and Python for model training.

Tech stack: Go, TypeScript, MySQL, gRPC, Protocol Buffers, Angular, AWS, Jenkins.

Co-founder and consultant at Octarine

June 2016 - January 2018

Built a small software design and development studio from scratch. I was responsible for many parts of the business, including payroll, finances, hiring, and training. Managed the entire lifecycle of projects, from pitching to delivery.

Full-stack engineer at Logimeter, a telecommunications company

November 2014 - January 2018

Hired as a front-end developer to build their AngularJS app, but soon began working with Python and Django in earnest. I mainly worked on development, infrastructure and maintenance of their application code and telecommunications infrastructure. Around this time I started to develop an interest in using statistical methods to build production features.

Full-stack engineer at Firing Squad, a web design agency

March 2012 - October 2014

Freelance HTML, CSS, and JS web site development

December 2011 - Feb 2012

Technical writer at Laragh Courseware

November 2010 - November 2011

Open-source contributions

- <u>Django SQL Explorer</u>: <u>Added Django 2.0 compatibility</u>
- Django
 - Fixed a bug in contrib.postgres
 - · Added the StrIndex database function
- Open edX: Various bugfixes and improvements
- REM unit polyfill: Added media query support

Education

- Licensed Scrum Master at <u>Scrum Inc.</u>: January 2020
- Deep Learning, a 5-course specialization by deeplearning.ai on Coursera: October 2018 April 2019
- Bachelor of Arts at the University of Cape Town: 2007 2009
 - Dual major in psychology and English literature

Languages

English: Native. German: Intermediate. Afrikaans: Elementary.